Okay, let's continue with the breakeven analysis with more than one alternative
starting with two alternatives that are mutually exclusive
typical example found in almost all books on engineering economy, business economics
is a two alternative breakeven analysis and typically is a make or buy analysis
so we have the choice between making something or buying something
if we buy something we will only have a variable cost, if we make something we will have a fixed cost
and an unvariable cost which obviously will be lower than if we buy it
otherwise it would be a very easy decision
here we have a breakeven value, we see that if we are having an amount that is higher than this breakeven point
it's more interesting to make everything that is below that breakeven point
it's more interesting to buy
okay, maybe a more realistic example
so we are talking about GARGEN, a company that is making home health care appliances
and it's a make or buy decision about a wheelchair lift to be used in a car
well actually it's about one of the parts of that lift
so they can buy that arm, that steel arm
so that means they outsource their production and then the cost is 0.6 per unit
or they can decide to manufacture it in house
then they need two machines, machine A with a cost of 18,000
a life of 4 years and a 2,000 salvage value which will need an overall after 3 years
and that will cost 3,000 dollars
it's an annual operating cost is 6,000 dollars per year
machine B has a 12,000 dollar cost, has a life of 4 years and a minus 500 salvage value
and it's operating cost is 5,000 dollars per year
now have a look at that salvage value, quite interesting
here we have a negative salvage value which means that we don't receive money
but we will have to pay money, they call it carry away cost
so that means that actually we have to pay a company that is coming to pick up our machine
and we have to pay them for that, we do not get any money
also we need operators, we need 4 operators, their cost is 12,5 per hour per operator
and in a normal shift of 8 hours they can make a 1,000 units
so he has to do two things
to compute the number of units to be manufactured each year to justify the make option
and if the company expects to produce 125,000 units per year
and every estimate remains the same, then what is then the maximum capital expense justifiable
so option 1 is outsourced and this is a very simple
it's too very simple, part of the equation that's minus 0.6 times x
x being the number of lifts to be produced per year
for our machine situation, so in-house situation
we have a variable cost and that variable cost is the cost of our operators
which we have there and of course we have the cost of our machines
which is given here for machine B, it's pretty simple
we only have a negative salvage value, we have an initial amount of money we need to invest
and we have our annual operating costs
for the first machine, machine A, we have our initial investment of 18,000
we have our salvage value of 2,000, positive 1 here
we have an annual operating cost of 6,000 and we also have this overhaul that we need to do after 3 years
bringing those together, so bringing these together gives us the second part of our equation
and that equation can also be used to solve the second part of the question
okay, now of course we can have more than two alternatives, we can have three alternatives
a typical example here is conceptualized in the right part
it's a choice between the appropriate level of automation
what you see here is, this is a throughput, so basically it's the number of operations that you do
for instance in a mechanical workshop or in a warehouse
this is the cost, if you have a manual system, well starting costs are pretty low
but variable cost is pretty high because each time that our throughput is increasing
we will have to hire new people and that's rather expensive
the other extreme is to go for a fully automated system
which will require quite a steep investment but then a rather low variable cost
so then the question is what is the most interesting situation
and you see when we have a low throughput we favor the manual one
if you have a very high throughput we go for a fully automated one
this is a conceptual picture, this is a picture that is actually made by ABB
about robots, so what they are comparing is the systems, manual assembly, human robot collaboration
so called co-bots, robotic automation or fixed automation
and we have the production volume, we have the cost
and what you see is that with a very low production volume manual still seems to be the most interesting one
if you go for a very large production volume then probably fixed automation is the best
and in between we have a human robot co-bot zone and a robot zone
so the breakeven is providing insight in these things
we will not talk about Excel if you are interested you can go for Excel yourself